<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deuout psalmes and colletes gathered and set in suche order, as may be vsed for dayly meditacions.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843526</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8265</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8265)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 483:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deuout psalmes and colletes gathered and set in suche order, as may be vsed for dayly meditacions.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Flete strete, at the signe of the Sunne, ouer agaynste the Conduyte, by Edwarde Whitchurche,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the .v. daye of Nouember, in the yeare of our Lorde. 1547.] Anno. 1.5.6.7. [i.e. 1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication, printer's name, and correct publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  A-G H² .</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 20478.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20478 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8265:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8265:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Deuout pſalmes and colletes, gathered and ſet in ſuche order, as may be vſed for dayly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions.</p>
            <p>Anno, 1.5.6.7.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb facs="tcp:8265:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶An exhortacion to prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Monges all other exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (good Chriſtian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that god hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs, that we may exerciſe oure ſelues in: there is none better, none more excellent, then is true prayer, cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a cleane hert, and an vnfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conſcience. For in the day of temta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion when the olde ſerpent by his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl ſuggeſtions ſhal go about our helth to ſubuert, we ſhal eaſely by prayer (as a preſent remedy) all hys malicyouſe &amp; ſondry dartes extynguiſhe. Alſo in the day of external affliccion (which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times chaunſeth for our ſinnes &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes) by prayer we ſhall eyther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne helpe that it may be mitigated, or elles all together taken away. Fyrſt of all, this is to be noted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt make our prayers and commen peticions vnto god, and to hym onely: For he is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of euery good and perfecte gifte. It is one chefe operacion and working be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto his diuinitie, to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs ſuche thinges as we doe aſke and craue of hym. They therfore that dooe aſke of other beſydes hym, (ſomuche as is in them) dooe rob god of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="tcp:8265:2"/> and diuinitie. It is written in the epiſtle of ſaynt Iames: If any of you want wiſdom, let him aſke of him that geueth it, that is of god. And god alſo by hys prophet Dauid exhorteth vs to make our prayers vnto him, his wordes be theſe: Cal vpon me in the day of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion, and I will delyuer the. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to thys ſaynt Paule ſayeth: How ſhall they call vppon him, in whom they beleue not. Therfore we cannot call on hym for help but in whome we dooe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue: we cannot beleue that oure peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ſhalbe graunted, excepte we be ſteyed vpon ſome promiſe made vnto vs in the ſcripture. The promyſe in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as concernyng our peticions to be graunted, is made by the father only, &amp; that in the name of Chriſt: wherfore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him only oure prayers is to be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Furthermore this is to be noted in prayer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt pray with our hartes and mindes, not onely with our lippes, &amp; our toung. For yf we do: we may well be compared vnto the Iewes, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſauiour Chriſt ſayde: o ye hipocrites Eſaie the prophet hath prophecied well of you, ſaying: This peopell draweth nere vnto me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there mouth, &amp; they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:8265:3"/> me with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyppes, but theyr heart is far from me. Let vs call to our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce the example of Anna mother of Samuel, whiche prayed vehemently vnto god, and her peticion was heard &amp; graunted, &amp; yet ſhe ſpake not one word with her toung: But powred furth the whole ſorow &amp; anguyſhe of her mynde afore god. And god ſayde vnto Moiſes, wherfore doeſt thou crye vnto me whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moyſes ſpake nothing with his toung, but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his hart. Therfore in our praiers let vs lift vp our heartes vnto God, earneſtly deſyring thoſe thinges, that we haue moſt nede of: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating our mindes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all cares and deſyres of the worlde, &amp; the fleſhe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8265:3"/>
            <div n="Monday" type="day">
               <head>On the mundaye.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt pſalme.</hi> Beatus vir qui non abiit.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed is that man, that hath not walked in the counſayl of the vngodly, nor ſtande in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of ſinners, and hath not ſit in the ſeate of the ſcorneful.</p>
                  <p>But his delyte is in the lawe of the Lord: and in his lawe wyl he exerciſe him ſelfe day and night.</p>
                  <p>And he ſhalbe like a tree pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the water ſyde, that wyl bryng furth his fruit in due ſeaſon</p>
                  <p>His leafe alſo ſhal not wither, &amp; loke whatſoeuer he doeth, it ſhal proſper.</p>
                  <p>As for the vngodly, it is not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8265:4"/> with them: but they are like the chaffe which the wynd ſcattereth away (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the yearth.)</p>
                  <p>Therfore the vngodly ſhal not be able to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the iudgement, neither the ſynners in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion of the righteous.</p>
                  <p>But the lord knoweth the way of the righteous, and the way of the vngodly ſhal periſhe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Verba mea auribus. Pſal. v.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Onder my wordes, o Lord, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditacion.</p>
                  <p>O herken thou vnto the voyce of my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, my kyng and my God, for vnto the wyll I make my praier.</p>
                  <p>My voyce ſhalt thou heare by tymes, o Lord, early in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng wyl I direct my praier vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:8265:4"/> the, and wyll loke vp.</p>
                  <p>For thou art the God that hath no pleaſure in wickednes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal any euil dwel with the.</p>
                  <p>Suche as be foliſhe, ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight, for thou hateſt al them that worke vanitie.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt deſtroye them that ſpeake leſyng: the Lord wyll ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre both the bloudthyrſty, and deceitful man.</p>
                  <p>But as for me, I wyl come into thy houſe, euen vpon the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy mercy, &amp; in thy feare wyll I worſhip towarde thy holy temple.</p>
                  <p>Leade me, o Lord, in thy right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſenes, becauſe of myne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: make thy way playne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my face.</p>
                  <p>For there is no faythfulnes in his mouth: theyr inwarde partes
<pb facs="tcp:8265:5"/> are very wickednes.</p>
                  <p>Their throte is an open ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre: thei flatter with theyr tong.</p>
                  <p>Deſtroy thou them O God, let them periſhe thorowe their owne ymaginacions, caſt them out in the multitude of theyr vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for they haue rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the.</p>
                  <p>And let all them that put theyr truſt in the, reioyce: thei ſhal euer be geuyng of thankes, becauſe thou defendeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thei that loue thy name ſhalbe ioyful in the.</p>
                  <p>For thou Lorde wylte geue thy bliſſyng vnto the righteous: and with thy fauourable kyndneſſe wylt thou defende him, as with a ſhilde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The third.</hi> Domine ne. Pſal. vi.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:5"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, rebuke me not in thine indignacion: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chaſten me in thy diſpleaſure.</p>
                  <p>Haue mercy vpon me, O lord, for I am weake: O lord heale me, for my bones are vexed.</p>
                  <p>My ſoule alſo is ſore troubled: but lord how long wilte thou pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe me?</p>
                  <p>Turne the, O lord, and deliuer my ſoule: Oh, ſaue me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                  <p>For in death no man remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth the: and who wyll geue the thankes in the pit?</p>
                  <p>I am weary of my gronyng, euery night waſhe I my bed, and water my couche with my teares</p>
                  <p>My beautie is gone for very trouble, &amp; worne away becauſe of all myne enemies.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:6"/>
                  <p>Away fro me all ye that worke vanitie: for the lorde hath hearde the voyce of my wepyng.</p>
                  <p>The lord hath heard my peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord wyl receiue my praier</p>
                  <p>All myne enemies ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded &amp; ſore vexed, they ſhalbe turned backe and putte to ſhame ſodenly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The fourth.</hi> Domine dominus noſter. pſal. viii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde oure gouernour, how excellent is thi name in all the world, thou that haſt ſet thy glory aboue the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens?</p>
                  <p>Out of the mouth of very ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and ſucklinges haſt thou or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſtrength, becauſe of thine enemies, that thou mighteſt ſtyll the enemye and the auenger.</p>
                  <p>For I wyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre thy heauens,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:6"/> euen the workes of thy fyngers: the Moone &amp; the ſtarres whiche thou haſt ordayned.</p>
                  <p>What is manne that thou art myndefull of him? and the ſonne of man that thou viſiteſt him?</p>
                  <p>Thou madeſt him lower then the Aungels, to croune him with glory and worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Thou makeſt him to haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the workes of thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: &amp; thou haſt put all thynges in ſubiection vnder his feete.</p>
                  <p>Al ſhepe and oxen, yea, and the beaſtes of the felde.</p>
                  <p>The foules of the ayre, &amp; the fyſhe of the ſea, and whatſoeuer walketh thorowe the pathes of the ſeas.</p>
                  <p>O lord oure gouernour, howe excellent is thy name in all the worlde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:7"/>
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God the father of mercy, and God of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, the whiche onely forgeueſt ſynne, forgeue vnto vs our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes good lorde, forgeue vnto vs our ſinnes, that by the multitude of thy mercy, thei may be couered and not imputed vnto vs, and by the operacion of the holy ghoſt, we may haue power and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth hereafter to reſiſt ſynne: by oure ſauiour &amp; lord Ieſu Chriſt. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>¶<hi>The Letany. The lordes praier, The twelue articles of our beliefe. The ten commaundementes. The places co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng Baptiſme. The places co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the ſupper of the lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Almighty God and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lord whiche geueſt. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Tuesday" type="day">
               <pb facs="tcp:8265:7"/>
               <head>On the tuyſday.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt.</hi> Saluum me fac. pſal. xii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Elpe (me) lord, for ther is not one godly man lefte.</p>
                  <p>For the faythfull are miniſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the children of men.</p>
                  <p>They talke of vanitie, euerye one with his neighbour: they do but flatter with theyr lippes, &amp; diſſemble in theyr double heart.</p>
                  <p>The Lord ſhall rote out all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptful lippes, and the tong that ſpeaketh proude thynges.</p>
                  <p>Whiche haue ſayd: with oure tongue wyll we preuayle: we are they that ought to ſpeake, who is lord ouer vs?</p>
                  <p>Now for the comfortleſſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſake of the neady, &amp; becauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe ſighyng of the poore,</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:8"/>
                  <p>I wyl vp (ſayth the lord) &amp; wyll helpe euery one, from him that ſwelleth againſt him, and wyl ſet them at reſt.</p>
                  <p>The wordes of the Lorde are pure wordes euen as the ſyluer, whiche from yearth is tried and purified ſeuen tymes in the fyre.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt kepe them (O lord) thou ſhalte preſerue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this generacion for euer.</p>
                  <p>The vngodly walke on euery ſide: when they are exalted, the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men are put to rebuke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Dixit inſipiens. pſal. xiiii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fole hath ſayd in his heart there is no God.</p>
                  <p>They are corrupt, and become abhominable in their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges, there is not one that doth good (no not one.)</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:8"/>
                  <p>The lord loked doune fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the children of men, to ſee if there were any that would vnderſtand &amp; ſeke after God.</p>
                  <p>But they are al gone out of the way, they are al together become abhominable: there is none that doth good, no not one.</p>
                  <p>Their throte is an open ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre: with their tonges thei haue diſceiued, the poyſon of aſpes is vnder their lippes.</p>
                  <p>Their mouth is ful of curſyng &amp; bitternes: theyr feete are ſwifte to ſhed bloud.</p>
                  <p>Deſtruction and vnhappynes is in their waies, and the way of peace haue they not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is no feare of God before their eyes.</p>
                  <p>Haue they no knowledge that they al are ſuche workers of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:9"/> eatyng vp my people as it were bread, &amp; cal not vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord.</p>
                  <p>There were they brought in great feare (euen where no feare was) for God is in the generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the righteous.</p>
                  <p>As for you, ye haue made a mocke at the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of the poore, becauſe he putteth his truſt in the lord.</p>
                  <p>Who ſhal geue ſaluacion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iſrael, out of Syon?</p>
                  <p>When the lord turneth the cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuitie of his people, then ſhal Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cob reioyce, &amp; Iſrael ſhalbe glad.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third.</hi> Domine quis habitabit. pſal. xv</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Orde who ſhall dwel in thy tabernacle? who ſhall reſt vpon thy holy hyl?</p>
                  <p>Euen he that leadeth an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt
<pb facs="tcp:8265:9"/> life, and doeth the thyng whiche is right, and ſpeaketh the truth from his heart.</p>
                  <p>He that hath vſed no diſceipte in his tong, nor done euil to his neighboure, and hath not ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred his neighbours.</p>
                  <p>He that ſetteth not by him ſelf: but is lowly in his owne eyes, &amp; maketh muche of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare the Lord.</p>
                  <p>He that ſweareth vnto his neighbour and diſapointeth him not, though it were to his owne hynderaunce.</p>
                  <p>He that hath not geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſury, nor taken reward againſt the innocent.</p>
                  <p>Who ſo doeth theſe thynges, ſhal neuer fal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fowerth.</hi> Deus deus meus. pſal. xxii.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, my God: (loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me) why haſt thou forſaken me: and art ſo farre fro my helth, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wordes of my complaint?</p>
                  <p>O my God, I crie in the day tyme, but thou heareſt not: &amp; in the night ſeaſon alſo, I take no reſt</p>
                  <p>And thou continueſt holye, O thou worſhip of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Our fathers hoped in the, they truſted in the, and thou diddeſt deliuer them.</p>
                  <p>They called vpon the, and wer helped: they put theyr truſt in the and were not confounded.</p>
                  <p>But as for me I am a worme and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: a very ſcorne of men, and the outcaſt of the people.</p>
                  <p>All they that ſee me, laugh me to ſcorne: they ſhote out theyr lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes
<pb facs="tcp:8265:10"/> and ſhake their head ſaiyng: He truſted in God that he would deliuer him: let him deliuer him if he wyl haue him.</p>
                  <p>But thou arte he that toke me out of my mothers wombe: thou waſt my hope when I ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged yet vpon my mothers breaſtes.</p>
                  <p>I haue bene left vnto the euer ſyns I was borne: thou arte my God euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</p>
                  <p>O go not fro me, for trouble is harde at hand, and there is none to helpe me.</p>
                  <p>Many oxen are come about me fatte bulles of Baſan cloſe me in on euery ſyde.</p>
                  <p>They gape vpon me with their mouthes as it were a rampyng and roryng Lyon.</p>
                  <p>I am poured out like water, &amp; all my bones are out of ioynte:
<pb facs="tcp:8265:11"/> my heart alſo in the middeſt of my bodye, is euen like meltyng waxe.</p>
                  <p>My ſtrength is dryed vp lyke a potſherde, and my tong cleueth to my gummes: and thou ſhalte bryng me into the duſt of death.</p>
                  <p>For (many) dogges are come a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout me, and the counſayle of the wicked lay ſiege againſt me.</p>
                  <p>They pearſed my handes, and my feete, I may tel al my bones: they ſtande ſtaryng and lokyng vpon me.</p>
                  <p>They parte my garmentes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and caſt lottes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my veſture.</p>
                  <p>But be not thou farre from me O lord: thou art my ſuccour, haſt the to helpe me.</p>
                  <p>Deliuer my ſoule from the ſwearde, my dearelyng from the
<pb facs="tcp:8265:11"/> power of the dogge.</p>
                  <p>Saue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyons mouth: thou haſt heard me alſo from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the hornes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnicornes.</p>
                  <p>I wyll declare thy name vnto my brethren: in the middeſt of the congregacion wyll I prayſe the.</p>
                  <p>O prayſe the lorde ye that feare him: magnifye him all ye of the ſeede of Iacob, and feare him all ye ſeede of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>For he hath not diſpyſed nor ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horred the lowe eſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore: he hath not hyd his face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, but when he called vnto him, he heard him.</p>
                  <p>My praiſe is of the in the great congregacion, my vowes wyll I perfourme in the ſight of them that feare him.</p>
                  <p>The poore ſhal eate, &amp; be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: they that ſeke after the lorde
<pb facs="tcp:8265:12"/> ſhal prayſe him, your heart ſhall liue for euer.</p>
                  <p>All the endes of the world ſhal remembre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the lord: and al the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redes of the nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhal worſhip before him.</p>
                  <p>For the kingdome is the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and he is the gouernour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people.</p>
                  <p>Al ſuche as be fat vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yearth, haue eaten &amp; worſhipped.</p>
                  <p>Al they that go doune into the duſt, ſhall kneele before him, and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath quickened his owne ſoule.</p>
                  <p>My ſeede ſhall ſerue him: they ſhalbe counted vnto the lord, for a generacion.</p>
                  <p>They ſhall come, and (the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens) ſhal declare his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vnto a people that ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:8265:12"/> borne, whom the lord hath made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Lord God whiche diſpiſeſt not a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trite heart, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteſt the ſinnes &amp; wickednes of a ſinner, in what houre ſoeuer he doth mourne and lament his old maner of liuyng: Graunt vnto vs O lorde now gathered to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thy name, true contricion of heart, that we may vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently diſpiſe our ſinnefull life paſt, and wholely be conuerted vnto the, by our ſauiour &amp; lorde Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
                  <p>The lordes praier. &amp;c. as vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monday.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Wednesday" type="day">
               <pb facs="tcp:8265:13"/>
               <head>On the wedniſday.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt.</hi> Ad te domine leuaui. pſal. xxv.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the (O lord) wyll I lift vp my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>My God, I haue put my truſt in the:</p>
                  <p>Oh let me not be confounded: neither let myne enemies triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph ouer me.</p>
                  <p>For all they that hope in the ſhall not be aſhamed: but ſuche as tranſgreſſe without a cauſe, ſhalbe put to confuſion.</p>
                  <p>Shewe me thy wayes O lord, and teache me thy pathes.</p>
                  <p>Leade me furth in thy trueth, and learne me, for y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> art the God of my ſaluacion: in the hath bene my hope al the day long.</p>
                  <p>Cal to remembraunce (O lord) thy tendre mercyes, and thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng kyndneſſes, whiche haue
<pb facs="tcp:8265:13"/> bene euer of olde.</p>
                  <p>Oh remembre not the ſynnes and offences of my youthe, but according vnto thy mercy thinke thou vpon me (O lorde) for thy goodnes.</p>
                  <p>Gracious &amp; righteous is the lorde, therfore wyll he teache ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the way.</p>
                  <p>Them that be meke ſhall he guide in iudgement, and ſuche as be gentle, them ſhal he learne his way.</p>
                  <p>All the pathes of the lorde are mercy and trueth, vnto ſuche as kepe his couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
                  <p>For thy names ſake O lord, be mercyful vnto my ſynne, for it is great.</p>
                  <p>What man is he that feareth the lord? him ſhal he teache in the
<pb facs="tcp:8265:14"/> way that he ſhal choſe.</p>
                  <p>His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, &amp; his ſeede ſhal inherite the lande.</p>
                  <p>The ſecrete of the Lorde is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that feare him, and he wyl ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his couenaunt.</p>
                  <p>Myne eyes are euer lokyng vnto the lord, for he ſhal plucke my feete out of the net.</p>
                  <p>Turne the vnto me, and haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me: for I am deſolate and in miſery.</p>
                  <p>The ſorowes of my heart are enlarged.</p>
                  <p>O bryng thou me out of my troubles.</p>
                  <p>Loke vpon myne aduerſitie &amp; miſery, &amp; forgeue me al my ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Conſidre myne enemies howe many they are, and they beare a a tyrannous hate againſt me.</p>
                  <p>O kepe my ſoule, and deliuer
<pb facs="tcp:8265:14"/> me: let me not be confounded, for I haue put my truſt in the.</p>
                  <p>Let perfectnes and righteous dealyng wayte vpon me, for my hope hath bene in the.</p>
                  <p>Deliuer Iſrael O God, out of al his troubles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Dominus illuminatio. pſal. xxvii</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lord is my light and my ſaluacion: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then ſhal I feare?</p>
                  <p>The lord is the ſtrength of my life: of whom then ſhall I be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde?</p>
                  <p>When the wicked (euen myne enemies &amp; my fooes) came vpon me, to eat vp my fleſhe, they ſtum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled and fel.</p>
                  <p>Though an hooſt of men were layd againſt me, yet ſhal not my heart be afrayde: &amp; though there
<pb facs="tcp:8265:15"/> roſe vppe warre agaynſt me, yet wyl I put my truſt in him.</p>
                  <p>One thyng haue I deſired of the lord, whiche I wyll require: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I may dwel in the houſe of the lord al the daies of my life to behold the fayre beauty of the lord: and to viſit his temple.</p>
                  <p>For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of trouble he ſhal hide me in his tabernacle: yea in the ſecrete place of his dwellyng ſhal he hide me, and ſet me vp v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a rocke of ſtone.</p>
                  <p>And now ſhall he lifte vppe my heade aboue mine enemies rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about me.</p>
                  <p>Therfore wyll I offre in his dwellyng, an oblacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with great gladnes.</p>
                  <p>I wyl ſyng and ſpeake prayſes vnto the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Herken vnto my voice O lord,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:15"/> when I cry vnto the, haue mercy vpon me, and heare me.</p>
                  <p>My heart hath talked of the: Seke ye my face: thy face O lord wyl I ſeke.</p>
                  <p>O hyde not thou thy face fro me, nor caſt thy ſeruaunt awaye in diſpleaſure.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt bene my ſuccoure, leaue me not, neither forſake me, O God of my ſaluacion.</p>
                  <p>When my father and mother forſake me, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord taketh me vp.</p>
                  <p>Teache me thy way O lord, &amp; leade me the right waye becauſe of myne enemies.</p>
                  <p>Deliuer me not into the wyll of myne aduerſaries, for ther are falſe wytneſſes riſen vp agaynſt me, and ſuche as ſpeake wrong.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould vtterly haue fainted but that I beleue verely to ſe the
<pb facs="tcp:8265:16"/> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the lorde in the land of the liuyng.</p>
                  <p>O tary thou the lordes leyſure, be ſtrong, &amp; he ſhal comfort thine heart, and put thou thy truſt in the lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third.</hi> In te domine ſperaui. pſal. xxxi.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the lord, haue I put my truſt: let me neuer be put to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me in thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
                  <p>Bowe doune thyne eare to me, make haſt to deliuer me.</p>
                  <p>And be thou my ſtrong rocke, &amp; houſe of defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that thou mayeſt ſaue me.</p>
                  <p>For thou art my ſtrong rocke, &amp; my caſtle.</p>
                  <p>Be thou alſo my guide, &amp; leade me for thy names ſake.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:16"/>
                  <p>Drawe me out of the net that they haue layde priuely for me, for thou art my ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>Into thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende my ſpirit: for thou haſt redemed me, O lorde thou God of truth.</p>
                  <p>I haue hated them that hold of ſuperſticious vanities, and my truſt hath bene in the lorde.</p>
                  <p>I wil be glad and reioyce in thy mercy: for thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidred my trouble, &amp; haſt knowen my ſoule in aduerſities.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt not ſhut me vp into the hande of the enemye, but haſt ſet my feete in a large rowme.</p>
                  <p>Haue mercy vpon me O lorde, for I am in trouble, &amp; myne eye is conſumed for very heuynes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen my ſoule and my body.</p>
                  <p>For my life is waxen olde with
<pb facs="tcp:8265:17"/> heauynes, and my yeares with mournyng.</p>
                  <p>My ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth fayleth me becauſe of myne iniquitie, and my bones are conſumed.</p>
                  <p>I became a reprofe among all myne enemies, but ſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my neighbours, and they of myne acquaintaunce were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde of me, and they that did ſe me without, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueied them ſelues fro me.</p>
                  <p>I am cleane forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a dead man out of mynde: I am become like a broken veſſel.</p>
                  <p>For I haue heard the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the multitude: and feare is on euery ſide whyle they conſpire together againſt me, &amp; take their counſail to take away my life.</p>
                  <p>But my hope hath bene in the, O lord, I haue ſayd: thou art my God.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:17"/>
                  <p>My tyme is in thy hande, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me from the hand of myne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and from them that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me.</p>
                  <p>Shewe thy ſeruaunt the light of thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce, and ſaue me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                  <p>Let me not be confounded, O lord, for I haue called vpon the: let the vngodly be put to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; be put to ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue.</p>
                  <p>Let the liyng lippes be put to ſilence, whiche cruelly, diſdayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, &amp; ſpitefully ſpeake agaynſt the righteous.</p>
                  <p>O how ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful is thy goodnes, whiche thou haſt layd vp, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare the? and that thou haſt prepared for them, that put theyr truſt in the, euen before the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of men?</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt hyde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuely by
<pb facs="tcp:8265:18"/> thyne owne preſence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokyng of all menne, thou ſhalt kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecretly in thy taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, from the ſtrife of tongues.</p>
                  <p>Thankes be to the Lorde: for he hath ſhewed me merueilous great kyndnes in a ſtrong cytie.</p>
                  <p>And when I made haſt, I ſayd: I am caſt out of the ſight of thine eyes.</p>
                  <p>Neuertheles, thou heardeſt the voyce of my prayer when I cried vnto the.</p>
                  <p>O loue the lord, all ye his ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, for the lorde preſerueth them that are faythful, and ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſly rewardeth he the proude doer.</p>
                  <p>Be ſtrong, and he ſhal ſtabliſhe your heart, all ye that put your truſt in the lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fowerth.</hi> Beati quorum. pſal. xxxii.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed is he, whoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes is forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and whoſe ſynne is couered.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed is the man, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord imputeth no ſinne, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</p>
                  <p>For while I helde my tongue, my bones co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed away thorow my dayly complainyng.</p>
                  <p>For thy hand is heuy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me day &amp; night, and my moyſture is like the drouth in ſummer.</p>
                  <p>I wyll knowledge my ſynne vnto the, &amp; myne vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes haue I not hid.</p>
                  <p>I ſayd: I wyl confeſſe my ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> forgaueſt the wickednes of my ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. Sela.</p>
                  <p>For this ſhall euerye one that is godly, make his praier. vnto the in a tyme when thou
<pb facs="tcp:8265:19"/> mayeſt be found, but in the great water fluddes they ſhal not come nigh him.</p>
                  <p>Thou art a place to hide me in, thou ſhalt preſerue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: thou ſhalt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe me aboute w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſonges of deliueraunce. Sela</p>
                  <p>I wyll enfourme the, &amp; teache the in the way wherin thou ſhalt goo: and I wyll guyde the with myne eye.</p>
                  <p>Be ye not like horſe and Mule, whiche haue no vnderſtandyng, whoſe mouthes muſt be holden with bitte and bridle, leſt they fal vpon the.</p>
                  <p>Great plages remayne for the vngodly, but whoſo putteth his truſt in the Lord, mercye embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him on euery ſyde.</p>
                  <p>Be glad, O ye righteous, and reioyce in the lord: and be ioyful
<pb facs="tcp:8265:19"/> al ye that are true of heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Mercifull father, by whoſe power and ſtrength we may ouer come our enemies both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ghoſtly: graunt vnto vs O Lorde that accordyng to oure promyſe made in Baptiſme we may ouercome the chief enemies of our ſoule, that is the deſyres of the world, the pleaſures of the fleſhe, and the ſuggeſtions of the wicked ſpirite, and ſo after leade our liues in holynes and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, that we may ſerue the in ſpirit and in trueth, &amp; that by our ſauiour &amp; lord Ieſu Chriſt. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>The letany. &amp;c. As on monday.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Almightye God &amp; merciful lord whiche geueſt. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Thursday" type="day">
               <pb facs="tcp:8265:20"/>
               <head>On the thurſday.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt.</hi> Benedicam dominum. Pſal. xxxiiii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wyl alway geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vnto the lorde, his prayſe ſhall euer be in my mouth.</p>
                  <p>My ſoule ſhall make her boſt in the lord, the humble ſhal heare therof, and be glad.</p>
                  <p>O praiſe the lord with me, and let vs magnifye his name toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>I ſought the Lord, &amp; he heard me: yea, he deliuered me out of al my feare.</p>
                  <p>They had an eye vnto him, &amp; were lightened, &amp; theyr faces wer not aſhamed.</p>
                  <p>Lo, the poore crieth, &amp; the lord heareth him, yea, and ſaueth him out of al his troubles.</p>
                  <p>The Angel of the lord tarieth
<pb facs="tcp:8265:20"/> rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about them that feare him, and deliuereth them.</p>
                  <p>O taſte &amp; ſee how gracious the Lorde is, bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him.</p>
                  <p>O feare the lorde, ye that be his ſainctes, for they that feare him lacke nothyng.</p>
                  <p>The lyons do lacke, and ſuffre hunger, but they whiche ſeke the Lorde, ſhall want no maner of thyng that is good.</p>
                  <p>Come ye children &amp; herken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, I wyl teache you the feare of the lord.</p>
                  <p>What man is he that luſteth to liue, and would fayne ſee good dayes?</p>
                  <p>Kepe thy tong fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil, and thy lippes that they ſpeake no guile.</p>
                  <p>Eſchewe euil and do good, ſeke peace and inſue it.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:21"/>
                  <p>The eyes of the Lorde are ouer the righteous, and his eares are open vnto theyr praiers.</p>
                  <p>The countenaunce of the lorde is againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do euil, to rote out the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the yearth.</p>
                  <p>The righteous crye, &amp; the Lord heareth them: and deliuereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of al theyr troubles.</p>
                  <p>The lorde is nigh vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are of a contrite heart, &amp; wyl ſaue ſuche as be of an humble ſpirite.</p>
                  <p>Great are the troubles of the righteous, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord deliuereth him out of al.</p>
                  <p>He kepeth all his bones, ſo that not one of them is broken.</p>
                  <p>But miſfortune ſhal ſlay the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly, &amp; they that hate the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, ſhalbe deſolate.</p>
                  <p>The lorde deliuereth the ſoules
<pb facs="tcp:8265:21"/> of his ſeruauntes: &amp; all they that put theyr truſt in him ſhal not be deſtitute.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Nolite emulare. pſal. xxxvii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ret not thy ſelfe becauſe of the vngodly: neither be thou enuious againſt the euil doers.</p>
                  <p>For they ſhal ſone be cut doune like the graſſe, &amp; be withered eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the grene herbe.</p>
                  <p>Put thou thy truſt in the lord, and do good: dwel in the lande &amp; verely thou ſhalt be fed.</p>
                  <p>Delite thou in the lorde, and he ſhall geue the thy heartes deſyre.</p>
                  <p>Commit thy way vnto the lord, and put thy truſt in him, and he ſhal bryng it to paſſe.</p>
                  <p>He ſhal make thy righteouſnes as clere as the light, and thy iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:8265:22"/> dealyng as the noone day.</p>
                  <p>Holde the ſtyl in the Lorde, and abyde pacientely vpon him: but grieue not thy ſelfe at him whoſe way doeth ꝓſpere againſt the man that doth after euil cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes.</p>
                  <p>Leaue of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrathe, and let go diſpleaſure: fret not thy ſelfe, els ſhalt thou be moued to do euil.</p>
                  <p>Wicked doers ſhalbe roted out and they that paciently abide the lord, thoſe ſhal inherite the land.</p>
                  <p>Yet a lytle while, &amp; the vngodly ſhalbe cleane gone: thou ſhalte loke after his place, and he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be away.</p>
                  <p>But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meke ſpirite ſhal poſſeſſe the yearth, and ſhalbe refreſhed in the multitude of peace.</p>
                  <p>The vngodly ſeketh counſail a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt the iuſt, and gnaſheth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:8265:22"/> him with his teethe.</p>
                  <p>The Lorde ſhal laugh him to ſcorne, for he hath ſeene, that his day is commyng.</p>
                  <p>The vngodly haue drawen out the ſwearde, &amp; haue bended theyr bowe, to caſt doune the pore and neady, and to ſlaye ſuche as be of right conuerſacion.</p>
                  <p>Theyr ſwearde ſhal go thorow theyr owne heart, and theyr bowe ſhalbe broken.</p>
                  <p>A ſmal thing that the righteous hath, is better then great riches of the vngodly.</p>
                  <p>For the armes of the vngodly ſhalbe broken, and the Lord vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth the righteous.</p>
                  <p>The Lord knoweth the daies of the godly, and theyr enheritance ſhal endure for euer.</p>
                  <p>They ſhal not he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded in
<pb facs="tcp:8265:23"/> the perilous tyme, &amp; in the daies of derth, they ſhal haue ynough.</p>
                  <p>As for the vngodly, they ſhal periſhe: and the enemyes of the Lord ſhall conſume as the fat of lambes, yea, euen as the ſmoke ſhal they conſume away.</p>
                  <p>The vngodly boroweth and payeth not againe, but the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is mercyful and liberal.</p>
                  <p>Suche as be bleſſed of God, ſhal poſſeſſe the land, &amp; they that be curſed of him ſhalbe roted out</p>
                  <p>The lord ordreth a good mans goyng, and maketh his way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Though he fal, he ſhal not be caſt a way, for the lord vpholdeth him with his hand.</p>
                  <p>I haue bene yong, &amp; nowe am old: &amp; yet ſawe I neuer the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous forſaken, nor his ſede beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng
<pb facs="tcp:8265:23"/> theyr bread.</p>
                  <p>The righteous is euer merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and lendeth, and his ſeede is bleſſed.</p>
                  <p>Fle from euil, &amp; do the thyng that is good: and dwel for euer.</p>
                  <p>For the lord loueth the thyng that is right, he forſaketh not his that be godly, but they are preſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued for euermore.</p>
                  <p>The vnrighteous ſhalbe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: as for the ſeede of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, it ſhalbe roted out.</p>
                  <p>The righteous ſhall enherite the lande, &amp; dwel therin for euer.</p>
                  <p>The mouthe of the righteous is exerciſed in wiſedome, and his tong wyll be talkyng of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>The lawe of his God is in his heart, and his goynges ſhall not ſlide.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:24"/>
                  <p>The vngodly ſeeth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſeketh occaſion to ſlaye him.</p>
                  <p>The lorde wyl not leaue him in his hande, nor condempne him when he is iudged.</p>
                  <p>Hope thou in the lord, and kepe his way, and he ſhal promote the that thou ſhalt poſſeſſe the land: when the vngodly ſhall periſhe, thou ſhalt ſe it.</p>
                  <p>I my ſelf haue ſene the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in great power, and floriſhyng like a grene bay tree.</p>
                  <p>I we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by, &amp; loe, he was gone: I ſought him, but (his place) could no where be found.</p>
                  <p>Kepe innocency, and take heede vnto the thyng that is right, for that ſhall bryng a man peace at the laſt.</p>
                  <p>As for the tranſgreſſours they
<pb facs="tcp:8265:24"/> ſhall periſhe together, &amp; the ende of the vngodly is, they ſhalbe ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out at the laſt.</p>
                  <p>But the ſaluacion of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of the lord, whiche is alſo theyr ſtrength in the tyme of trouble.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord ſhal ſtand by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſaue them: he ſhal deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the vngodly, and ſhal ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they put theyr truſt in him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The third.</hi> Dixi cuſtodiam vias. pſal. xxxix.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Sayd: I will take hede to my wayes, that I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende not in my tong.</p>
                  <p>I wil kepe my mouth (as it wer with a bridle) while the vngodly is in my ſight.</p>
                  <p>I helde my tong, and ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:25"/>
                  <p>I kept ſilence: yea, euen from good wordes, but it was payne and grefe to me.</p>
                  <p>My heart was hote within me and while I was thus muſyng, the fyre kyndled: and (at the laſt) I ſpake with my tong.</p>
                  <p>Lord, let me know myne ende, &amp; the numbre of my dayes: that I may be certified how lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I haue to liue.</p>
                  <p>Beholde, thou haſt made my daies as it were a ſpanne long, &amp; myne age is euen as nothyng in reſpecte of the: and verely euery man liuyng is altogether vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Sela.</p>
                  <p>For man walketh in a vayne ſhadowe, &amp; diſquieteth him ſelfe in vayne, he heapeth vp riches &amp; cannot tel who ſhal gather them.</p>
                  <p>And nowe Lorde, what is my
<pb facs="tcp:8265:25"/> hope? truely my hope is euen in the.</p>
                  <p>Deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all mine offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and make me not a rebuke vnto the foliſhe.</p>
                  <p>I became dumme, and opened not my mouth, for it was thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng.</p>
                  <p>Take thy plage away fro me: I am euen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy heuy hand.</p>
                  <p>When thou with rebukes doſt chaſten man for ſynne, thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt his beauty to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume away, like as it were a moth frettyng a garment.</p>
                  <p>Euery man therfore is but va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie. Sela.</p>
                  <p>Heare my praier, O lorde, and with thine eares conſidre my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng: holde not thy peace at my teares.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:26"/>
                  <p>For I am a ſtraunger with the &amp; a ſoiourner, as all my fathers were.</p>
                  <p>Oh ſpare me a lytle, that I may recouer my ſtrength, before I go hence, and be no more ſene.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The fourth.</hi> Beatus qui intelligit. Pſal. xli.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed is he that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the poore (and nedy) the Lord ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of trouble.</p>
                  <p>The lord preſerue him &amp; kepe him aliue: that he may be bleſſed vpon yearth, &amp; deliuer not thou him into the wyl of his enemies.</p>
                  <p>The lord comfort him, when he lyeth ſicke vpon his bed: make thou al his bed in his ſicknes.</p>
                  <p>I ſayd, lord be mercyfull vnto me, heale my ſoule, for I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned againſt the.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:26"/>
                  <p>Myne enemyes ſpeake euil of me: when ſhall he dye, and his name periſhe?</p>
                  <p>And if he come to ſe me, he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vanitie, and his heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth falſhod within him ſelfe: and when he commeth furth, he telleth it.</p>
                  <p>All myne enemies whiſper to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt me: euen againſt me do they ymagine this euil.</p>
                  <p>Let the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of giltynes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cede againſt him, and nowe that he lyeth, let him riſe vp nomore.</p>
                  <p>Yea euen myne owne familiar frende who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I truſted (whiche did alſo eate of my bread) hath layde great wayte for me.</p>
                  <p>But be thou merciful vnto me (O lord) raiſe thou me vp again, and I ſhal rewarde them.</p>
                  <p>By this I knowe thou fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb facs="tcp:8265:27"/> me, that myne enemye doeth not triumph againſt me.</p>
                  <p>And when I am in my helth: thou vpholdeſt me, and ſhalt ſet me be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore thy face for euer.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, worlde without ende. Amen and Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Almighty and euerlaſtyng God, whiche not onely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt euery good and perfite gift, but alſo encreaſeſt thoſe gyftes that thou haſte geuen, we mooſt humbly beſeche the mercyfull God, to encreaſe in vs the gift of fayth, that we may truely beleue in the and in thy promiſes made vnto vs, and that neither by our negligence nor infirmitie of the fleſhe, nor by greuouſnes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, neither by the ſubtil craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:8265:27"/> and aſſaultes of the deuill, we be driuen from fayth in the bloud of oure ſauioure and lorde Ieſu Chriſte. Amen.</p>
                  <p>The lordes prayer. &amp;c. as afore.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Friday" type="day">
               <head>On the Fridaye.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſte.</hi> Miſerere mei deus. pſal. li.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aue mercy vpon me (O God) after thy greate goodnes: according vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the multitude of thy mercies, do away myne offences.</p>
                  <p>Waſh me throwly fro my wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, &amp; clenſe me from my ſin.</p>
                  <p>For I knowlege my faultes, &amp; my ſin is euer before me.</p>
                  <p>Agaynſt the only haue I ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned and doen this euill in thy ſyghte: that thou myghteſt be iuſtified in
<pb facs="tcp:8265:28"/> thy ſaying, and cleare when thou art iudged.</p>
                  <p>Behold, I was ſhapen in wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kydnes, and in ſinne hath my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceyued me.</p>
                  <p>But lo thou requireſt truth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward partes, &amp; ſhalt make me to vnderſtand wiſdome ſecretly.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt pourge me with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope, and I ſhall be cleane: thou ſhalt waſhe me, and I ſhalbe why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſnowe.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt make me heare ioye and gladnes, that the bones which thou haſt broken, maye reioyce.</p>
                  <p>Turne thy face from my ſinnes, and put out all my myſdedes.</p>
                  <p>Make me a cleane hert (O god) &amp; renewe a right ſpirite within me.</p>
                  <p>Caſt me not away from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and take not thy holy ſpirite from me.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:28"/>
                  <p>O geue me the comfort of thy helpe agayne: &amp; ſtablyſhe me with thy fre ſprete. Then ſhal I teache thy wayes vnto the wicked, and ſinners ſhalbe conuerted vnto the.</p>
                  <p>Delyuer me from bloud gylty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (O God) thou that art the God of my health, and my tonge ſhall ſinge of thy ryghteouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt open my lippes, (O Lord) &amp; my mouth ſhal ſhewe thy prayſe.</p>
                  <p>For thou deſyreſt no ſacrifice, els woulde I geue it the: but thou delyteſt not in burnt offerynge.</p>
                  <p>The ſacrifyce of god is a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſpirite, a broken and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite hert (O God) ſhalt thou not diſpyſe.</p>
                  <p>O be fauourable &amp; gracious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sion, buyld thou the walles of Ieruſalem.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:29"/>
                  <p>Then ſhalt thou be pleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſacrifice of righteouſneſſe with burnt offerynges and oblacions, then ſhall they offer younge bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes vpon thyne aultare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Quid gloriaris. pſalm. l.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hy boaſteſte thou thy ſelfe, thou tirant, that thou canſt do miſchif? Where as the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God endureth yet dayly.</p>
                  <p>Thy tong ymagineth wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and with lyes thou curteſt like a ſharpe raſour.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt loued vngraciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes more then goodnes: &amp; to talke of lyes more then ryghteouſnes. Sela.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſte loued to ſpeake all wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maye do hurte, O thou falſe tonge.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:29"/>
                  <p>Therfore ſhall God deſtroye the for euer, he ſhall take the and plucke the out of thy dwelling, and roote the out of the lande of the liuing. Sela.</p>
                  <p>The righteous alſo ſhall ſee this, &amp; feare: and ſhal laugh him to ſcorne.</p>
                  <p>Lo, this is that man that toke not God for his ſtrength, but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vnto the multitude of his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, &amp; ſtrengthed him ſelfe in hys wickednes.</p>
                  <p>As for me I am lyke a grene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyue tree in the houſe of God, my truſt is in the tender mercy of god for euer and euer.</p>
                  <p>I wil alway geue thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the: for that thou haſt done: &amp; I will hope in thy name, for thy ſaynctes lyke it well.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:30"/>
                  <head>¶<hi>The third.</hi> Deus in nomine tuo. pſal. liiii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aue me (O God) for thy names ſake, and auenge me in thy ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>Heare my prayer (O God) and herken vnto the wordes of my mouth.</p>
                  <p>For ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers are riſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp againſt me, and tirauntes (which haue not God before their eyes) ſeke after my ſoule. Sela.</p>
                  <p>Beholde God is my helper, the Lorde is with them that vpholde my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall reward euel vnto mine enemies: deſtroy thou them in thy truthe.</p>
                  <p>An offrynge of a free herte will I geue the, and prayſe thy name (O Lord) bicauſe it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable.</p>
                  <p>For he hath delyuered me out of all my trouble, and myne eye hath
<pb facs="tcp:8265:30"/> ſene his deſyre vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine enemies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The fourth.</hi> Exaudi deus. Pſal. lv.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eare my prayer (O God) and hyde not thy ſelfe fro my peticion.</p>
                  <p>Take hede vnto me, &amp; heare me, howe I mourne in my prayer, and am vexed.</p>
                  <p>The enemye cryeth ſo, and the vngodly commeth on ſo faſt: for they are mynded to doo me ſome myſchefe, ſo maliciouſly are they ſet agaynſte me.</p>
                  <p>My hert is diſquieted within me, and the feare of death is fallen vpon me.</p>
                  <p>Fearfulneſſe and trembling are come vpon me, &amp; an horrible drede hath ouerwhelmed me.</p>
                  <p>And I ſayde: O y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had winges like a doue, for then wold I flye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp; be at reſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:31"/>
                  <p>Lo, then would I get me away far of, and remaine in the wyldre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Sela.</p>
                  <p>I would make haſte to eſcape, becauſe of the ſtormy wynde and tempeſt.</p>
                  <p>Deſtroy their tonges o lord, and deuide them: for I haue ſpied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes &amp; ſtryfe in the citie.</p>
                  <p>Day and nyght go they about within the walles therof: miſchief alſo, and ſorow are in the middeſt of it.</p>
                  <p>Wickedneſſe is therein, diſceat, and gyle go not out of her ſtretes.</p>
                  <p>For it is not an open enemye that hath done me this diſhonour: for then I coulde haue borne it: nether was it mine aduerſary, that did magnifye hym ſelfe agaynſte me: for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture) I would haue hyd my ſelfe from hym.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:31"/>
                  <p>But it was euen thou my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, my gyde, and myne owne familier frende.</p>
                  <p>We toke ſwete counſayle toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and walked in the houſe of god, as frendes.</p>
                  <p>Let death come haſtily vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and let them go doune quicke into hel, for wickednes is in their dwel lynges, and among them.</p>
                  <p>As for me I wyl cal vnto god, and the lorde ſhall ſaue me.</p>
                  <p>In the euening and mornynge and at the none day wil I praye, (and that inſtantlye) and he ſhall heare my voyce.</p>
                  <p>It is he that deliuereth my ſoule in peace, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the battayl that was agaynſt me: for there were many with me.</p>
                  <p>Ye euen god that endureth for euer, ſhall heare me: and brynge
<pb facs="tcp:8265:32"/> them downe. Sela.</p>
                  <p>For they wyl not turne nor feare god.</p>
                  <p>He layde his handes vpon ſuche as be at peace with hym, and he brake his couenaunte.</p>
                  <p>The wordes of his mouth were ſofter then butter, hauing war in hys harte: hys wordes were ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then oyle, and yet be they ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſweardes.</p>
                  <p>O caſt thy burthen vpon the Lord, &amp; he ſhal noryſh the: &amp; not ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous to fall for euer.</p>
                  <p>And as for them, thou (O god) ſhalt brynge them into the pyt of deſtruccion.</p>
                  <p>The bludthurſtie and dyſceat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men ſhall not lyue out halfe their dayes.</p>
                  <p>Neuertheles, my truſt ſhalbe in the (O Lorde.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:32"/>
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>GRaunte vnto vs O merciful god we moſt hartely beſeche, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge &amp; true vnderſtanding of thy worde, that al ignorance ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, we may knowe what thy wyl and pleaſure is in al thinges, and howe to do our duties, &amp; truly to walke in our vocacion, &amp; that alſo we maye expreſſe in oure ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thoſe thynges that we doo knowe: that we be not only knowers of thy worde good lorde, but alſo be workes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: by our ſauiour &amp; Lorde Ieſu Chriſte. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>¶The Letany. &amp;c. As afore.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Saturday" type="day">
               <pb facs="tcp:8265:33"/>
               <head>On ſatterday.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt.</hi> Eripe me de inimicis. pſal. lix.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Elyuer me from myne enemyes (O God) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me from them that ryſe vp agaynſte me.</p>
                  <p>O deliuer me from the wicked doers, &amp; ſaue me from the bloude thurſty men.</p>
                  <p>For lo, they lye waytyng for my ſoule, the mightye men are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together agaynſt me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anye offence or faute of me (O Lorde.)</p>
                  <p>They runne and prepare them ſelues, without my faute.</p>
                  <p>Aryſe, thou therfore to help me, and beholde.</p>
                  <p>Stande vp (O Lorde God of hooſtes) thou God of Iſraell, to viſet al Heathen: and be not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull vnto them that offende of
<pb facs="tcp:8265:33"/> malicious wickednes. Sela.</p>
                  <p>They go to &amp; fro in the euening, they grenne lyke a dogge, &amp; runne aboute thorowe the cytie.</p>
                  <p>Behold, they ſpeake with theyr mouth, and ſweardes are in theyr lyppes for who doth heare?</p>
                  <p>But thou (O Lorde) ſhalt haue them in deryſion, and thou ſhalte laugh all Heathen to ſcorne.</p>
                  <p>My ſtrength wil I aſcribe vnto the, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of my refuge.</p>
                  <p>God ſheweth me his goodnes plenteouſlye, and god ſhall let me ſee my deſyre vpon myne enemies.</p>
                  <p>Slaye them not, leſt my people forget it: but ſcatter them abrode amonge thy people, and put them downe (O Lorde) our defence.</p>
                  <p>For the ſinne of theyr mouth, and for the wordes of theyr lippes they ſhalbe taken in their pryde,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:34"/> and why? theyr preachinge is of curſynge and lyes.</p>
                  <p>Conſume them in thy wrath, conſume them that they maye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, and knowe that it is God whych ruleth in Iacob, and vnto the endes of the worlde. Sela.</p>
                  <p>And in the euenyng they wyl re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: grenne like a dogge and wil go aboute the cytie.</p>
                  <p>They will runne here and there for meate, and grudge yf they be not ſatiſfyed.</p>
                  <p>As for me, I wyll ſinge of thy power: and wyll prayſe thy mercy be times in the morning, for thou haſte bene my defence and refuge in the day of my trouble.</p>
                  <p>Vnto the, O my ſtrength, wyl I ſyng, for thou (O God) art my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and my mercyfull god.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Exau di deus depreca. Pſal. lxi.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eare my crying (o god) geue eare vnto my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.</p>
                  <p>From the endes of the earth wil I cal vnto the, when my hert is in heuines.</p>
                  <p>Oh ſette me vp vpon the rocke that is hygher then I.</p>
                  <p>For thou haſt bene my hope, and a ſtronge tower for me, agaynſte the enemye.</p>
                  <p>I will dwell in thy tabernacle for euer, &amp; my truſt ſhalbe vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coueryng of thy wynges. Sela.</p>
                  <p>For thou O Lord, haſt heard my deſires, &amp; haſt geuen an heritage vnto thoſe that feare thy name.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt graunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king a long lyfe, that hys yeares may endure thoroweout al generacions.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:35"/>
                  <p>He ſhall dwell before God, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: O prepare thy louing mercy &amp; faythfulnes, that they may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue him:</p>
                  <p>So wil I alway ſing prayſe to thy name, that I maye dayly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme my vowes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third.</hi> Nonne deo ſubiecta: pſal. lxii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſoule trulye wayteth ſtil vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, for of him cometh my ſaluacion.</p>
                  <p>He verely is my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; my ſaluacion: He is my defence ſo that I ſhal not greatly fal.</p>
                  <p>Howe long will ye ymagin miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chife agaynſt euerye man? ye ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſlayne all the ſorte of you: yea, as a totteryng wall ſhal ye be, and lyke a broken hedge.</p>
                  <p>Theyr deuice is only howe to put hym out, whom God will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alte:
<pb facs="tcp:8265:35"/> their delyght is in lyes: they geue good woordes wyth theyre mouthe, but curſe with theyr hert. Sela.</p>
                  <p>Neuertheles, my ſoule wayt thou ſtyll vpon god, for my hope is in hym.</p>
                  <p>He truely is my ſtrength, &amp; my ſaluacion: he is my defence ſo that I ſhall not fall.</p>
                  <p>In god is my helth and my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, the rocke of my might, and in God is my truſt.</p>
                  <p>O put your truſt in him alway (ye people) poure out youre hertes before hym, for God is our hope. Sela.</p>
                  <p>As for the chyldren of men, they are but vayne, the children of men are diſceatful vpon the wayghtes they ar altogether lyghter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie it ſelfe.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:36"/>
                  <p>O truſt not in wronge and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berye, geue not youre ſelues vnto vanitie: yf ryches increaſe, ſet not your hert vpon them.</p>
                  <p>God ſpake once and twyſe: I-haue alſo heard the ſame: that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer belongeth vnto god.</p>
                  <p>And that thou Lorde art mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull, for thou rewardeſte euery man accordinge to hys worke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The fourth.</hi> Deus miſereatur noſtri. pſal. lxvii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od, be merciful vnto vs, and bleſſe vs, and ſhewe vs the lyght of of hys countenaunce: (and be mercifull vnto vs). Sela.</p>
                  <p>That thy waye maye be knowen vpon earth, thy ſauing helthe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all nacions.</p>
                  <p>Let the people prayſe the O god: yea, let all the people prayſe the</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:36"/>
                  <p>O let the nacyons reioyce and be glad: For thou ſhalt iudge the folke righteouſly, &amp; gouerne the nacions vpon earth. Sela.</p>
                  <p>Let the people prayſe the O god, let all thy people prayſe the.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhal the earth bring forthe her encreaſe, &amp; God euen our owne God ſhall geue vs his bleſſynge.</p>
                  <p>God ſhall bleſſe vs, and all the endes of the world ſhal feare hym.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Almightie god, whiche haſt prepared euerlaſtyng lyfe to all thoſe that be thy faythful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, graunt vnto vs Lorde ſure hope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life euerlaſting, that we beyng in this miſerable worlde may haue ſome taſte, and feling of it in our hartes: and that not by
<pb facs="tcp:8265:37"/> our deſeruing, but by the merites and deſeruing of our ſauiour, and Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Ieſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
                  <p>¶The Letany. &amp;c. As afore.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Saturday afternoon" type="day">
               <head>On ſatterday at after noone.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt</hi> Voce mea ad dominum. pſal. lxxvii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wyll crye vnto God wyth my voyce, euen vnto God will I crye with my voyce: and he ſhall herken vnto me.</p>
                  <p>In the tyme of my trouble, I I ſought the Lord: my ſore ranne and ceaſſed not in the nyght ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: my ſoule refuſed comforte.</p>
                  <p>When I am in heuineſſe, I wil thynke vpon God, when my herte is vexed, and wil complayne. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:37"/>
                  <p>Thou holdeſt mine eies waking: I am ſo feble, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I cannot ſpeake.</p>
                  <p>I haue conſidered the dayes of olde, and the yeares that are paſt.</p>
                  <p>I call to remembraunce my ſonge: and in the nyght I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with myne owne harte, and ſearche out my ſpirites</p>
                  <p>Wyll the lorde abſent him ſelfe for euer? And wil he be no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated.</p>
                  <p>Is hys mercy cleane gone for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? and is his promiſe come vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to an ende for euermore?</p>
                  <p>Hath God forgotten to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious? And will he ſhut vp hys lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe in diſpleaſure? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</p>
                  <p>And I ſayd: it is mine owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmitie: But I wil remembre the yeres of the right hand of the moſt hyeſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:38"/>
                  <p>I will remembre the workes of the Lorde, and call to minde thy wonders of olde tyme.</p>
                  <p>I will thinke alſo of all thy workes, and my talking ſhalbe of thy doynges.</p>
                  <p>Thy waye, O God, is holie: who is ſo great a God as (oure) God? Thou art the god that doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres, and haſt declared thy power among people.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt mightely delyuered thy people, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonnes of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob and Ioſeph. Sela.</p>
                  <p>The waters ſawe the, O god, the waters ſawe the and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depthes alſo were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
                  <p>The cloudes powred out wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the ayre thundred: and thine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes went abrode.</p>
                  <p>The voyce of thy thundre was
<pb facs="tcp:8265:38"/> herd round about, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lighteninges ſhone vpon the grounde, the earth was moued and ſhoke withall.</p>
                  <p>Thy waye is in the ſea, and thy pathes in the great waters: &amp; thy footeſteppes are not knowen.</p>
                  <p>Thou lededſt thy people lyke ſheepe, by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Deus venerunt gentes pſal. lxxix.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God, the Heathen are come into thy enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, thy holy temple haue they defiled, and made Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an hepe of ſtones.</p>
                  <p>The dead bodies of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes haue they gyuen to be meate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the foules of the ayre, and the fleſhe of thy ſaynctes vnto the beaſtes of the lande.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:39"/>
                  <p>Their bloud haue they ſhed like water on euery ſide of Ieruſalem, &amp; ther was no man to bury them.</p>
                  <p>We are become an open ſhame vnto our enemies, a very ſcorne &amp; deriſion vnto them that are round about vs.</p>
                  <p>Lorde, howe longe wilt thou be angrye? ſhall thy gelouſye burne lyke fyre for euer?</p>
                  <p>Poure out thyne indignacion vpon the Heathen that haue not knowen the, and vpon thy kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes that haue not called vpon thy name.</p>
                  <p>For they haue deuoured Iacob, &amp; layed waſte his dwellyng place.</p>
                  <p>O remembre not our olde ſinnes, but haue mercy vpon vs, and that ſoone: for we ar come to great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.</p>
                  <p>Helpe vs O God of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:39"/> for the glory of thy name.</p>
                  <p>O delyuer vs, and be mercyful vnto oure ſynnes, for thy names ſake.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore do the Heathen ſaye: where is nowe theyr God?</p>
                  <p>O let the vengeaunce of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes bloude that is ſhed, be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſhewed vpon the Heathen, in our ſight.</p>
                  <p>O let the ſorowful ſyghynge of the priſonners come before the: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng vnto the greatneſſe of thy power: preſerue thou thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are appoynted to dye.</p>
                  <p>And as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemy (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with oure neyghbours haue blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the) reward thou them O Lorde, ſeuen folde into theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
                  <p>So we that be thy people, and ſhepe of thy paſture, ſhal gyue the
<pb facs="tcp:8265:40"/> thankes for euer, and wyl alway be ſhewyng forth thy prayſe, from generacion to generacion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third.</hi> Qui regis Iſrael. Pſal. lxxx.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eare O thou ſhepherd of Iſrael, thou that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Ioſeph like a ſhepe ſhew thy ſelfe alſo thou that ſitteſt vpon the Cherubins.</p>
                  <p>Before Ephraim, Beniamin, &amp; Manaſſes: ſtyre vp thy ſtrength, and come helpe vs.</p>
                  <p>Turne vs agayne O god, ſhewe the light of thy countenaunce, and we ſhalbe whole.</p>
                  <p>O Lord God of hooſtes, howe longe wilt thou be angry with thy people that prayeth?</p>
                  <p>Thou fedeſt them with the bread of teares, and giueſt them plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of teares to drinke.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:40"/>
                  <p>Thou haſt made vs a very ſtrife vnto our neighbours: and oure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies laugh vs to ſcorne.</p>
                  <p>Turne vs agayne, thou God of hooſtes, ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce: and we ſhalbe whole.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt brought a vine out of Egipt: thou haſt caſt out the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and planted it.</p>
                  <p>Thou madeſt rowme for it, and whan it had taken rote, it filled the lande.</p>
                  <p>The hylles were couered with the ſhadowe of it, &amp; the boughes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodly Cedre trees.</p>
                  <p>She ſtretched out her braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnto the ſea, &amp; her boughes vnto the ryuer.</p>
                  <p>Why haſt thou then broken downe her hedge, that all they whiche go by, plucke of her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:41"/>
                  <p>The wild bore oute of the wood doth rote it vp, &amp; the wilde beaſtes of the filde deuoureth it.</p>
                  <p>Turne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> agayne, thou God of hooſtes, loke downe from heauen: beholde, and viſit thys vyne.</p>
                  <p>And the place of the vyneiarde that thy right hand hath planted: &amp; the braunche that thou madeſt ſo ſtronge for thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>It is brent with fyre, and cut downe, &amp; they ſhall peryſhe at the rebuke of thy countenaunce.</p>
                  <p>Let thy hand be vpon the man of thy ryghte hande and vpon the ſonne of man whom thou madeſt ſo ſtronge for thyne owne ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>And ſo wyll not we go backe from the: Oh, let vs lyue, and we ſhall call vpon thy name.</p>
                  <p>Turne vs agayne, O lord god
<pb facs="tcp:8265:41"/> of hooſtes, ſhewe the lyght of thy countenaunce, &amp; we ſhalbe whole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The forthe.</hi> Inclina domine aurem. pſal. lxxxvi.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Owe downe thine eare, o lorde, and heare me, for I am poore and in miſery.</p>
                  <p>Preſerue thou my ſoule, for I am holye: my God ſaue thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> putteth his truſt in the.</p>
                  <p>Be mercifull vnto me (o Lord) for I will call dayly vpon the,</p>
                  <p>Coumfort the ſoule of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, for vnto the (o lorde) doe I lyft vp my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>For thou Lord art good &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and of great mercy vnto all them that call vpon the.</p>
                  <p>Geue eare Lord vnto my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ponder the voyces of my humble deſyres.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:42"/>
                  <p>In the tyme of my trouble I will call vpon the, for thou heareſt me.</p>
                  <p>Among the goddes there is none lyke vnto the, (O Lorde) there is not one that can do as thou doeſt.</p>
                  <p>All nacions whom thou haſte made, ſhall come and worſhyp the (O Lorde) and ſhall gloryfie thy name.</p>
                  <p>For thou art greate and doeſte wonderous thinges, thou art god alone.</p>
                  <p>Teache me thy waye (O Lorde) and I will walke in thy truth.</p>
                  <p>O knyt my hert vnto the, that it maye feare thy name.</p>
                  <p>I wyll thanke the, O Lorde my God with all my herte, and wyll prayſe thy name for euer.</p>
                  <p>For greate is thy mercy towarde me, and thou haſte delyuered my
<pb facs="tcp:8265:42"/> ſoule from the nethermoſt hell.</p>
                  <p>O god, the proude are ryſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and the congregacions of naughtie men haue ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my ſoule, and haue not ſet the before theyr eyes.</p>
                  <p>But thou (O Lorde god) arte full of compaſſion, &amp; mercy, longe ſufferyng, plenteous in goodnes and truth.</p>
                  <p>O turne the then vnto me and haue mercy vpon me: geue thy ſtrength vnto thy ſeruaunte, and helpe the ſonne of thyne hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayde.</p>
                  <p>Shewe ſome token vpon me for good, that they which hate me, maye ſe it: &amp; be aſhamed, becauſe thou Lorde haſt helped me and comforted me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:43"/>
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Mercifull God, oure only ayde, ſoccour, and ſtrength at all tymes, graunt vnto vs, O-lord, that in the tyme of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we be not proude, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the, but that with our whole power &amp; ſtrength, we may cleaue vnto the: and in the time of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie that we fall not to infidelitie, and deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that alwayes with a conſtante fayth we may cal for helpe vnto the: Graunte this O Lord for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates ſake, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Ieſu Chriſte. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>The Lordes prayer. &amp;c. As afore.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Sunday" type="day">
               <pb facs="tcp:8265:43"/>
               <head>On the Sunday.</head>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fyrſt.</hi> Domine refugium. pſal. xc.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord, thou haſt ben oure refuge from one genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion vnto another.</p>
                  <p>Before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mountaynes were brought forthe, or euer the earth and the worlde were made, thou art God from euerlaſtyng &amp; worlde without ende.</p>
                  <p>Thou turneſt man to deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayne thou ſayeſt: come agayne children of men.</p>
                  <p>For a thouſande yeares in thy ſyght are but as yeſterdaye, ſeyng that is paſte as a watche in the night.</p>
                  <p>As ſone as thou ſcatereſt them, they are euen as a ſlepe, and fade awaye ſodenlye lyke the graſſe.</p>
                  <p>In the mornynge it is grene and
<pb facs="tcp:8265:44"/> groweth vp, but in the eueninge it is cutte downe (dried vp) and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</p>
                  <p>For we conſume away in thy dyſpleaſure, and are afrayed at thy wrathfull indignacion.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt ſet our miſdedes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the, and oure ſecret ſynnes in the lyght of thy countenaunce.</p>
                  <p>For when thou arte angry, all our dayes are gone: we bring our yeares to an ende, as it were a tale that is tolde.</p>
                  <p>The dayes of our age are thre ſcore yeares and ten: and though men be ſo ſtronge that they come to foure ſcoure yeares, yet is their ſtrength, then but laboure and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe: ſo ſoone paſſeth it awaye, &amp; we are gone.</p>
                  <p>But who regardeth the power
<pb facs="tcp:8265:44"/> of thy wrath: for euen therafter as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fareth, ſo is thy dyſpleaſure.</p>
                  <p>O teache vs to noumbre our dayes, that we maye applye our hertes vnto wyſdome.</p>
                  <p>Tourne the agayne, (O Lord) at the laſt, and be gracious vnto thy ſeruauntes.</p>
                  <p>O ſatiſfie vs with thy mercy &amp; that ſoone, ſo ſhall we reioyce and be glad al the dayes of our lyfe.</p>
                  <p>Comforte vs agayne, nowe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time that thou haſt plaged vs, and for the yeares wherein we haue ſuffred aduerſitie.</p>
                  <p>Shewe thy ſeruauntes thy worke, &amp; theyr children thy glorie.</p>
                  <p>And the glorious maieſtie of the lorde our god be vpon vs: proſper thou the worke of our handes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, o proſper thou our handy worke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond.</hi> Venite exultemus. pſal. xcv.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Come, let vs ſynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, let vs her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely reioyce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of oure ſaluacion: let vs come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his preſence with thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and ſhewe our ſelfe glad in him with pſalmes.</p>
                  <p>For the Lorde is a great kinge aboue all goddes.</p>
                  <p>In his hand are all the corners of the earth, and the ſtrength of the hylles is hys alſo.</p>
                  <p>The ſea is hys, and he made it, and his handes prepared the drye lande.</p>
                  <p>O come, let vs worſhyppe and falle downe before the Lorde, our maker.</p>
                  <p>For he is (the Lorde) our God: and we are the people of hys pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:45"/> and the ſhepe of his handes.</p>
                  <p>To day if ye wil heare his voyce, harden not your hartes: as in the prouocacion, and as in the daye of tentacion in the wildernes: when youre fathers tempted me, proued me: &amp; ſawe my workes.</p>
                  <p>Fourtie yeares long was I gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the generacion, &amp; ſayde: it is a people that do erre in theyr hertes: for they haue not knowen my wayes.</p>
                  <p>Vnto whom I ſware in my wrath, that they ſhoulde not enter into my reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>¶<hi>The third.</hi> Iubilate deo. pſal. C.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Be ioyfull in the Lorde (all ye landes) ſerue the Lorde with gladneſſe: &amp; come before hys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with a ſong.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:46"/>
                  <p>Be ye ſure that the Lorde he is God: It is he that hath made vs, and not we our ſelues, we are hys people, &amp; the ſhepe of his paſture.</p>
                  <p>O go youre waye into his gates with thankeſgeuing, and into his courtes wyth prayſe, be thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vnto hym, and ſpeake good of hys name.</p>
                  <p>For the Lord is gracious, hys mercy is euerlaſtyng, &amp; his truthe endureth from generacion to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fowerth.</hi> Benedic anima mea. pſal. ciii.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rayſe the lorde, O my ſoule, &amp; al that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me prayſe hys holy name.</p>
                  <p>Prayſe the Lorde, O my ſoule, and forget not all hys benefytes.</p>
                  <p>Whiche forgeueth al thy ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:46"/> and healeth all thyne infyrmyties.</p>
                  <p>Whyche ſaueth thy lyfe from deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and crowneth the with mercye and louynge kyndneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Whiche ſatiſfyeth thy mouth with good thynges, makyng the yonge and luſtye as an Aegle.</p>
                  <p>The lorde executeth ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and iudgement, for all them that are oppreſſed with wronge.</p>
                  <p>He ſhewed his wayes vnto Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hys workes vnto the chyldren of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>The lorde is full of compaſſion and mercy: long ſuffring, and of great goodnes.</p>
                  <p>He wil not alway be chiding, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kepeth he his anger for euer.</p>
                  <p>He hath not dealt wyth vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our ſynnes, nor rewarded vs accordyng to our wickedneſſes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:47"/>
                  <p>For loke howe hye the heauen is in compariſon of the earth, ſo greate is hys mercy alſo towarde them that feare him.</p>
                  <p>Loke howe wyde alſo the Eaſt is from the weſt, ſo farre hath he ſet oure ſynnes from vs.</p>
                  <p>Yea lyke as a father pytieth hys owne children, euen ſo is the lorde merciful vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare him.</p>
                  <p>For he knoweth wherof we be made, he remembreth that we are but duſt.</p>
                  <p>The dayes of man are but as graſſe, for he floriſheth as a floure of the fielde.</p>
                  <p>For as ſone as the winde goth ouer it, it is gone: and the place therof ſhall knowe it no more.</p>
                  <p>But the mercifull goodneſſe of the lorde endureth for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that feare hym, and
<pb facs="tcp:8265:47"/> hys ryghteouſnes vpon childres children.</p>
                  <p>Euen vpon ſuche as kepe hys couenaunt, and thinke vpon hys commaundementes to do them.</p>
                  <p>The lorde hath prepared hys ſeate in heauen, and his kyngdom ruleth ouer all.</p>
                  <p>O prayſe the lorde ye Angels of hys, ye that excell in ſtrength: ye that fulfill hys commaundement, and herken vnto the voyce of hys wordes.</p>
                  <p>O prayſe the Lord al ye his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, ye ſeruauntes of hys, that do hys pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>O ſpeake good of the lorde all ye workes of hys, in all places of hys dominyon: prayſe thou the lorde, O my ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:48"/>
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Almyghtie &amp; mercifull lorde whiche geueſt vnto thy elect people the holy gooſte, as a ſure pledge of thy heauenly kyngdom: Graunte vnto vs o lorde, this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite, that he may beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with our ſpirite that we be thy children, and heyres of thy kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that by the operacion of this ſpirite we may kyl all carnall luſtes, vnlawfull pleaſures, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence euell affeccions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto thy wil: by our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure and lorde Ieſu Chriſt. A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="litany">
               <pb facs="tcp:8265:48"/>
               <head>The Letany.</head>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſinners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O God the father of heauen, haue mercye vpon vs myſerable ſynners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O God the ſonne, redemer of the worlde: haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſynners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O God the ſonne redemer of the worlde: haue mercy vpon vs myſerable ſinners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O God the holy goſt, proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng from the father &amp; the ſonne: haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſinners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O God the holy goſt, procedyng from the father and the ſonne: haue mercie vpon vs miſerable ſynners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O holy, bleſſed, and glorious Trinitie, three perſons and one God: haue mercy vpon vs miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſynners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:49"/>
                  <p>O holy, bleſſed, and glorious Trinitie, thre perſons and one God: haue mercy vpon vs miſerable ſynners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Holy virgin Mary, mother of God, our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Pray for vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>All holy Angels and Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, and all holy orders of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirites.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Pray for vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>All holy Patriarkes, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, Apoſtles and Martyrs, Confeſſours and Virgins, and all the bleſſed company of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Pray for vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Remembre not Lorde, oure offences, nor the offences of oure forefathers, neyther take thou vengeaunce of our ſinnes, ſpare vs good Lorde, ſpare thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom thou haſt redemed with thy moſte precious bloude, and
<pb facs="tcp:8265:49"/> be not angrye with vs for euer:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Spare vs good lorde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>From all euel and miſchiefe, from ſynne, from the craftes &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſautes of the deuyl, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy wrath, and from euerlaſting damnacion:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde deliuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>From blindneſſe of heart, from pryde, vayneglory, and hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, from enuy, hatred, and malyce, and all vncharitableneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde deliuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>From fornicacion, and all deadly ſynne, and from all the deceiptes of the worlde, the fleſſhe, and the deuyll:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde delyuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>From lightening and tempeſt, from plage, peſtilence, and famine: from battayle and murder, &amp; from ſodeyne death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:50"/>
                  <p>Good lorde delyuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>From all ſedicion, and pryuye conſpiracy, from the tyranny of the byſhop of Rome, and all hys deteſtable enormities, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all falſe doctrine and hereſy: from al hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, and contempt of thy worde and commaundement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde delyuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>By the miſtery of thy holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnacion, by thy holy Natiuitie &amp; circumciſion, by thy baptiſme, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng and temptacion:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde delyuer vs</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>By thyne agony and bluddy ſweat, by thy croſſe and paſſion, by thy precious death and bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, by thy glorious reſurrection and aſcencion, by the cummyng of the holy goſt:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde delyuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:50"/>
                  <p>In al tyme of our tribulacion, to all tyme of our welth, in the houre of death, in the day of iudgement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Good lorde delyuer vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>We ſynners do beſeche the to heare vs, O lorde God, and that it maye pleaſe the to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne thy holy churche vniuerſall in the ryght way:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lord:</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to kepe Edward the ſixt, thy ſeruaunt, &amp; our kyng and gouernour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to rule his heart in thy fayth, feare, and loue, that he maye euer haue affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce in the, and euer ſeke thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and glory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde:</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to be
<pb facs="tcp:8265:51"/> his defender &amp; keper, geuing him the victory ouer all his enemies:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to kepe the noble Quene Katherine dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier in thy feare and loue, geuing her increace of all godlyneſſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and children.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs Good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the lady Maries grace, the lady Elizabethes grace, and the Lorde Protectors grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate all byſhopes, paſtours, and myniſters of the Churche, with true knowledge, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng of thy worde, and that both by their preaching and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, they may ſet it furthe, and
<pb facs="tcp:8265:51"/> ſhewe it accordyngly:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the lordes of the counſayl, and al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobilitie, with grace, wiſdom, and vnderſtandyng:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs Good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to bleſſe and kepe the magiſtrates, geuing them grace to execute iuſtice, and to mayntayne truthe:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to bleſſe and kepe all thy people:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to geue to all nacions, vnitie, peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to geue vs an hearte to loue and dreade
<pb facs="tcp:8265:52"/> the, and diligently to lyue after thy commaundemente:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde:</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to geue all thy people increaſe of grace, to heare mekely thy worde, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it with pure affeccion, and to bring furth the fruites of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to bring into the way of truthe, all ſuche as haue erred, and are deceyued:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lord:</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it maye pleaſe the to ſtrengthen ſuche as do ſtande, and comfort and helpe the weake hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to rayſe vp them that fall, and finally to beate downe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan vnder our feete:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:52"/>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, helpe, and comfort all that be in daunger, neceſſitie, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all that trauayle by lande or by water, all women labourynge of childe, all ſicke perſons &amp; yong children, and to ſhew thy pitie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all priſoners and captiues:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and prouide for the fatherles children and widowes, &amp; all that be deſolate and oppreſſed:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to haue mercy vpon all men:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue
<pb facs="tcp:8265:53"/> our enemies, perſecutours, and ſclaunderous, &amp; to turne their heartes:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to geue to our vſe the kindely fruites of the yearth, ſo as in due tyme we may enioy them, and to preſerue them:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe the to geue to vs true repentaunce, to forgeue vs al our ſynnes, negligences and ignoraunces, &amp; to endue vs with the grace of thy holy ſpirite, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende oure lyues accordyng to thy holy worde:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We beſeche the to heare vs good lorde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Sonne of God, we beſeche the to heare vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sonne of god, we beſeche the to heare vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:53"/>
                  <p>O lambe of God that takeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſynnes of the worlde:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Graunte vs thy peace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O lambe of God that takeſt away the ſynnes of the worlde:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>O Chriſt heare vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Chriſt heare vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs:</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lorde haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>Our father which art in heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With the reſidue of the pater noſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>And ſuffre vs not to be led in to temptacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But delyuer vs from euyll. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>¶The verſicle.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:54"/>
                  <p>O lorde, deale not with vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our ſynnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>¶The anſwere.</head>
                  <p>¶Neyther rewarde vs after our iniquities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Let vs pray.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> God, mercifull father, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſeſt not the ſighing of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite hearte, nor the deſyre of ſuche as be ſorowfull, mercifully aſſiſt our prayers that we make before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in all oure troubles and aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when ſoeuer they oppreſſe vs.</p>
                     <p>And graciouſly heare vs, that thoſe euils, whiche the crafte and ſubteltie of the Deuyll or manne worketh againſt vs, be brought to nought, and by the prouidence of thy goodnes, they may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed, that we thy ſeruauntes,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:54"/> being hurte by no perſecucions, may euermore geue thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the, in thy holy Churche, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſu Chriſt our lorde.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>O lorde ariſe, helpe vs and delyuer vs for thy names ſake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>O God, we haue hearde with our eares, and our fathers haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared vnto vs the noble workes that thou dyddeſt in their dayes, &amp; in the olde tyme before them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>O lord ariſe, helpe vs, and delyuer vs, for thy honour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Glory to the father, the ſonne, &amp; to the holy goſt: as it hath bene from the beginning, is, and ſhalbe euer world without ende. Amen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>From our enemyes defende vs O Chriſt:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Graciouſly loke vpon our affliccions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8265:55"/>
                     <p>Pitifully beholde the dolour of our heart:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Mercyfully forgeue the ſynnes of thy people.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Fauourably with mercy heare our prayers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O ſonne of Dauid, haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Both nowe and euer vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaufe to heare vs Chriſt:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Graciouſly heare vs, O Chriſt:</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Graciouſly heare vs, O Lorde Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>¶The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>O lord, let thy mercy be ſhewed vpon vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>¶The anſwere.</head>
                  <p>As we do put our truſt in the.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶Let vs pray.</head>
                  <p>WE humbly beſeche the, O father, mercifully to looke vpon our infirmities, and for the glory of thy names ſake,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:55"/> turne from vs all thoſe euylles, that we mooſt ryghteouſly haue deſerued. Graunt this, O lorde God, for our mediatour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate Ieſu Chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> God, whoſe nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie is euer to haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and to forgeue, receyue oure humble peticion, and though we be tied and bound with the chayne of our ſynnes, yet let the pityful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy great mercy leuſe vs, for the honour of Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, our mediatour &amp; aduocate. Amen.</p>
                  <p>ALmyghty and euerliuyng God, whiche onely workeſt greate meruayles, ſende downe vpon oure byſhoppes and cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:56"/> and all congregacions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, the health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpirit of thy grace, and that they may truly pleaſe the: poure vpon them the continuall dewe of thy bleſſing. Graunt this (o lorde) for the honour of our aduocate &amp; mediatour Ieſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
                  <p>WE beſeche the (O Lorde) to ſhewe vpon vs thyne exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great mercye, whiche no tonge can worthely expreſſe, and that it may pleaſe the to delyuer vs from all oure ſynnes, and alſo from the paynes that we haue for them deſerued. Graunte this (O lord) through our mediatour and aduocate Ieſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
                  <p>GRaunt, we beſeche the, O al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, that we in our
<pb facs="tcp:8265:56"/> trouble, put our whole confidence vpon thy mercy, that we agaynſt all aduerſitie be defended vnder thy protection. Graunte this, O lorde God, for our mediatour and aduocate Ieſu Chriſtes ſake.</p>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
                  <p>ALmighty God, whiche haſt geuen vs grace at thys tyme with one accord to make our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune ſupplicacions vnto the, and doeſt promyſe, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two or .iii. be gathered in thy name, thou wilt graunt their requeſtes, fulfil now O lorde, the deſires and peticions of thy ſeruauntes, as may be beſt expedient for them, grauntyng vs in thys worlde, knowledge of thy truthe, and in the worlde to come lyfe euerlaſtyng. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="Pater_Noster">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:57"/>
                  <head>The prayer of our Lord.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr father whiche arte in heauen, halowed be thy name. Thy kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come. Thy wil be done in yearth as it is in heauen. Geue vs this day our daily bread. And forgeue vs our treſpaces, as we forgeue them that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs. And let vs not be led into temptacion. But delyuer vs from euill. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="creed">
                  <head>¶The Crede, or .xii. articles of the Chriſten fayth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleue in God the father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty, maker of heauen and yearth. And in Ieſu Chriſt hys only ſonne our Lorde. Whyche was conceyued of the holye goſt, borne of the virgin Mry. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnder Ponce Pylate, was crucified, dead, buryed, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, in to hell. And the thirde
<pb facs="tcp:8265:57"/> day, he roſe agayne from death. He aſcended into heauen, and ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the righte hande of god the father almightie. From thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleue in the holye goſte. The holy Catholycke churche. The Communion of ſaynctes: the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of ſynnes. The reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the body. And the life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="ten_commandments">
                  <head>¶The .x. commaundementes. of almighty God.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>THou ſhalte haue none other goddes in my ſyghte:</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalt make the no gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ymage, neyther any ſimilitude that is in Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, eyther in the earth beneth, or in the waters vnder the earthe.</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalte not worſhippe them,
<pb facs="tcp:8265:58"/> neyther ſerue them: for I the Lord thy god, am a gelouſe God: &amp; vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitte the ſynne of the fathers vpon the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the thyrd &amp; fourth generacion of theym that hate me: and ſhewe mercy vnto thouſandes in them that loue me and kepe my commaundementes.</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lorde thy god in vayne.</item>
                        <item>Remember the Sabboth daye, that thou ſanctifie it.</item>
                        <item>Honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that thy dayes maye be long in the lande, whiche the Lorde thy god geueth the.</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalte not kyll.</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalt not breake wedlocke.</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalte not ſteale.</item>
                        <item>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe agaynſte thy neyghboure. Thou ſhalte not couet thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures
<pb facs="tcp:8265:58"/> houſe: neyther ſhalt thou couet thy neyghbours wife, or hys manne ſeruaunte, or hys mayde, or his Oxe, or his aſſe, or what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thy neyghbour hath.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The places of baptyſme.</head>
                  <p>Go ye therefore,<note place="margin">Math. xxviii.</note> and teache all nacions, baptiſynge them in the name of the father, &amp; of the ſonne, and of the holy gooſte: Teaching them to obſerue al thinges, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer I haue commaunded you.</p>
                  <p>Go ye in to al the world &amp; preach the goſpel to all creatures,<note place="margin">Marke. xv</note> he that beleueth &amp; is baptiſed, ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But he that beleueth not, ſhal be dampned.</p>
                  <p>Knowe ye not that al we which are baptyſed into Ieſu Chriſt,<note place="margin">Roma. vi</note> are baptiſed to dye with hym?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:59"/>
                  <p>For ye are al children of god, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye beleue in Chriſt Ieſu.<note place="margin">Gal. iii.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For all ye that are baptyſed, haue put on Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>For the ſupper of the lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. xxvi.</note>When they were eatynge Ieſus toke breade, and whan he had ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thankes, he brake it, and gaue it to the dyſciples, &amp; ſayde: Take, eate, this is my body. And he toke the cuppe, and thanked, and gaue it them, ſaying: Drinke ye all of this, for this is my bloude (whiche is of the newe teſtamente) that is ſhed for many, for the remiſſion of ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Marke. xiiii.</note>And as they did eate, Ieſus toke breade: and whan he had geuen thankes, he brake it, and gaue to them and ſayd: Take, eate, thys is my bodie: And he toke the cup, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had geuen thankes, he toke
<pb facs="tcp:8265:59"/> it to them, and they all dranke of it, and he ſayde vnto them: Thys is my bloud of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe teſtament, whiche is ſhed for many.</p>
                  <p>And he toke breade, and when he had geuen thankes he brake it, and gaue vnto them ſaying.<note place="margin">Luke. xxii.</note> Thys is my body, whiche is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for you. This do in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of me. Lykewiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when he had ſupped, he toke the cuppe ſaying: This cup is the newe teſtament in my bloud, whiche is ſhed for you.</p>
                  <p>That which I delyuered vnto you, I receyued of the lorde.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> For the Lord Ieſu the ſame night, in whiche he was betrayed, toke breade: and when he had geuen thankes, he brake it, and ſayde: Take ye, and eate: this is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye; whiche is broken for you.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8265:60"/>
                  <p>This do ye in the remembraunce of me. After the ſame maner alſo he toke the cup; when ſupper was doen, ſaying: this cup is the newe Teſtament in my bloud. Thys dooe as oft as ye drinke it, in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membraunce of me. For as often as ye ſhall eate this bread: and drinke of this cup, ye ſhall ſhewe the Lordes deathe tyll he come. Wherfore, whoſoeuer ſhall eate of thys breade, or drynke of the cuppe of the Lord vnworthelye, ſhalbe gyltie of the body and blood of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>But let a man examin hymſelfe, and ſo let hym eate of the bread, &amp; drinke of the cup. For he that eateth and drinketh vnworthely, eateth &amp; drinketh hys owne da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, becauſe he maketh no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Lordes body. For
<pb facs="tcp:8265:60"/> this cauſe many are weake &amp; ſicke amonge you, &amp; manye ſlepe. For yf we had iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ourſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we ſhoulde not haue ben iudged.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8265:61"/>
            <p>¶<hi>Imprinted <hi>at London, in Flete ſtrete,</hi>
               </hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Sunne, ouer agaynſte</hi> the Conduyte, by Edwarde Whit-churche, the .v. daye of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember, in the yeare of oure Lord. <hi>1547.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <hi>ſolum.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8265:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
